Okay, my dawn hey there's my voice.
Here...about...
Can you talk?
Checker.
Right good.
So, trying to see back there.
Man when I start talking it's going to get really loud holding only.
... I look at the cfour ready to go.
Looking in the back of aren.
We rolling we ready to go.
Are we ready to start the presentation yet we're up okay?
Hello, everybody now that we have that out of the way welcome to your next session of the
day thanks everybody for showing up I'm jason also number program manager on the creative
media experiences team in os g of microsoft and this is my partner in crime
I'm baller...kumar a program manager on the creative media experience esteem would
jason and I handle the audio side of things so out of curiosity how many people in the audience
have actually built hey I recommend so many faces it makes me smile how many people
have actually built...like an audio or video out before.
...good number of
...how many of you are csharp developers.
How many of you people are cplus-plus developers how many people like writing cplus-plus
versus csharp?
Good how many people of the cplus-plus developers have written media foundation
and media foundation transform code how many of those of you that have done that enjoyed the
process.
Okay,...all hazard...that's what...kind of figure okay well we have some good stuff
for you today then I'm just going-to go ahead and dive into this quick
...business thing remember to fill
in evaluation form or you guys have seen this I'm just going to skip this...the end of the talk.
So, other things as a create a person myself outside of work I'm a musician
...a lot of creative work one the things that I love is no matter where I
go I always have some type of device within reach so
whenever that inspiration hits I can go ahead and capture that on my
...reach over and capture that latest song idea
the latest film idea and really just go with it before the
...leaves me the problem is to really have a great experience doing this
you need to have great apps that you can interact with as a user and what
we're here to talk about is really how are we making it better to build those great apps for all of
you so we really want to talk about the story of building these great creative
and video apps really easily on the windows ten platform so diving into this today
there's a couple areas that we're going to talk about we're going to talk about
kind of the video editing experience and what we're doing around creative video we're going to talk about
the creative audio side of things and what we're doing there as well as
touching on some music oriented apis like...and stuff like that to tell you how
...evolved in the last year...course we just want to focus on
...demos lots of code to show you guys all of this stuff hopefully all
this stuff working on the bits that you have available to go grab and start using today?
So, first let's talk about creative video experiences
when we actually take a look back and look at how media editing
exists today let's say on windows three-point-one.
Yes, we have a fully customizable video editing experience
...media foundation very powerful there's a lot of things you can do
...requires a lot of lower-level code requires a lot
of domain expertise and frankly takes a lot of code to do even the most
basic of scenarios like let's say I want to do basic things like combining one video
onto another video...to overlay one video on another video I want to work with
those videos by let's say adding a background audio track or something like that any of those
scenarios that should ultimately be really easy...kind of the basic scenarios...creative
video experience becoming incredibly difficult when you're having to do with media foundation today.
one of the things that we did that we announced last year build is on windows phone eight-point
one we introduce this new media composition api that makes it super simple
which...a couple lines of code to do the basic things like trimming a video
stitching different videos together adding background audio so on now to show that
an action let's say I want to do a simple thing where I just want to trim
twenty two seconds from a file well once again we're talking about just a couple
lines of code here to do this kind of thing let's say I want to build a slide show where I want to
take my favorite thirty photos and come...have each of them displayed
for ten seconds and then encode that to a video and be able to send it out
to my favorite social network or what have you once again with media composition in windows
phony point one this became a lot more simple to do where
...just talking about us add the photos as media clips
...this composition and you can dot you...bind that composition to a media elements
use media trance coder anything to say that out very simple?
But, one of the things at the start of windows ten.
We started asking ourselves okay that's great and all but what do we need
to do necks what's kind of the next things that need to be done
and one of the first things we realised any of you been in the video space for a while
...started to realize video starting to...be
a stagnant thing anymore the order static piece of content that you work with
a used to be that maybe I have a bunch of video files on my computer that I grab those
I manipulate them I edit them and then I produce some video file on the output
what we're seeing now is video is becoming a lot more about interactivity what are the ways that users are
wanting to interact with the videos and one of the cool things is those interactions
are actually starting to be captured in the content itself so some great work from partners like...
smith with their coaches I app vanessa...movie maker app and even our own hollow
...product you see this idea that now I'm annotating on a video I'm
eating on top of it I'm wanting to manipulated in some way and those actions that I'm taking
with the video are the things I want to capture naturally save out so then we
started to look okay this is great we introduce some cool features and windows sony point one that a lot of people really
enjoy how do we take this role of interactive ness and bring it
to windows ten well the first kind of obvious step is we need to take this media
composition api and bring it to the universal windows platform so now media
composition you-can use this regardless of what device running as long as...university as long as
...universal windows platform device so you can run it on your xbox you
can run on windows phone you can run on windows write the code once and that exact same code
ones on all the different device families.
But, then there was still a gap we
...that's great for the basic scenarios like trimming in stitching
and adding audio but the other ways that you want to interact with video creating cool of
...maybe overlaying one video on top of another video maybe I want to
overly photos on top of photos or any combination of the sorts.
You know, those were once again immediate steps where you could use media composition for the
basic things...was designed for but then you ultimately fell off this...this clip
of complexity we're now you have to down dive down back in the media foundation
...working in cplus-plus again so we added some cool things in windows
ten that bridges that gap...you have to draw a to have to fall off the cliff we want
to keep you in the things that keep you focused on adding user value
to your experiencing that will keep your users coming back for more.
So, rather than talk...show you all this kind of stuff I just want to coded
...I would rather drop in the visual studio switches over and show you some of this an action.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to first leverage the basic stuff that we did
around media composition and we'll see this app in action in a
...the first thing I need to do is create a media clip?
I've already have the user pick from a storage file and then I can just take that media clip
in I can go ahead and add it to our composition and now we have a media clip to work
with well we were talking about the our of overlays now to actually make this and overlays the
great thing about the overly support now in media composition with windows ten is
that overlays also build on top of media clips so anything that could be source from a media clipper
foreign image of file of photo what color can also be used
as overlays so let's go ahead and add some overlays.
What I'm going to do...up here I'm going-to go ahead and
add-in overlay layer which we'll talk in a minute what in overlay layer is?
Media a
cane composition overlay layers and I'm going to add that overlay layer.
Now of course now we have this overly layer think about
an overly layer as kind of like a container it's something that we can throw a bunch
of overlays into so-if you want-to do twelve overlays and keep them in one rendering
paths or you want to animate them together or something you can group them together in this concept
...layer will actually show one of the other cool things custom composite errors
are made possible with this idea of overlay layers but let's go ahead before we do that let's go ahead and
add some overlays.
Once again I mention so-you creamed overlay and we're going to add that media overlay to
our overly layer that we added and you can see the media overlay we just paths
...the clip the rest is
basically the position that we want to overlay and we can give it a capacity and that kind of thing.
what actually this to show you how many overlays we can handle let's do the same thing
...add the ability of doing some other overlays as well?
Go ahead and run this now this project you'll notice...all csharp.
It's real when we get further long you'll see that one
...when two-d to do a lot of cool stuff in the overlays and effects and with
the new when two-d support all that kind of stuff but the reason it takes longer to compile is of course
...using project and to compile this all natively.
So, let's go ahead and add a base video.
...going to add and overlay if I play...
You can see the top left.
We have one video that we've overlaid on top of another video once again
no graphical hiccups or anything like that the top left actually has opacity so you can see the
bottom layer through it really easy just once again couple lines of code to get this but,
you know, are not all impressed by that...what I want...a couple more?
I heard people really like photos of kids so I'm going to add a couple overlays from.
My first son about six years ago.
Let's play this now you can see were overlying for videos on top of a
...video and each one of them have opacity
...managing that once again we're talking about just a couple lines of code rather
than the literally thousands of lines of...have taken in media foundation.
Once again cool nice and simple really easy I like this.
You know, that's not
all that special let's start showing you some of the cool stuff that we can actually start doing so I'm going to
come over here and when I create that layer one of the things...notices
there's an overload for media overlay layer where I can actually pass in a custom composite
...definition so I have a custom...we're going to build here?
Let me give it.
...so we're going to use this example composite or that I've...
And, in this example composite or if I go here an example
composites just something that implements this new uw p interface I video composite
or if we can go there and the methods that are most relevance.
...to use this composite frame method that we'll give you all the surfaces that you need to
overlay and then you give us the output frame on the...which we'll see in a minute and
then setting coding properties will tell you how the videos encoded and give you the direct
three-b device so then you can use directory...when
two-d even use anything like that to actually do your overlays with which is actually what we're going to do
you how many people did any of you in the...talk before this online
...okay just a couple so you guys are going to see some fun stuff here
where what I'm going to do.
This is...two-d so once again we're all in csharp and I have.
This composite frame contacts where if I go into the definition of that we
give you the background frame which is the base that your overlying on top of
...we give you a bunch of surfaces to overlay which you'll see all these are just
I direct three-d surfaces so anything that can work
with those basic interfaces and interop with those basic interfaces you can use to implement a
...custom composite roars and effects as we'll see now and then you just give us
the output frame so what I've done in this setup is I've created
the output surface from that output frame on the context and then I've created a
rendell target in a drawing session which are from one to the to basically be able to
draw to it so of course one thing that I want to do is I want to go ahead
...I don't want...search.
I want to.
Get all the surfaces that we want to overlay.
And, one thing you'll notice a from then I look at this member we were we specified like
the position and the opacity and all that kind of stuff but at this point we're just dealing with
the interop types...direct three-d surface so it's just directory d surface we
want to go get that original overlay as well which you can do directly off the context object
as well so I'm going to say overlaying context.
Get overlay for surface and I'm going to pass in that surface were overlaying and then I want to
draught so.
Rectangles are boring so let's actually draw the videos as
...lips is just to see if we...
I'm pretty sure we can at least the other times I've run this demo it's worked so,
I'll let's draw the overlays.
You can see I'm creating a canvas image brush and other
when to deconstruct from the from the bitmap which is essentially
the overly surface that we've given and then I'm using...
with that brush to actually paint the image onto
the overlay and the output frame now something else
...have heard common feedback about is this is great
...then people a basic scenario that they might want to use text overlay I want
to actually overly a like a title slide or something like that on top of a video.
Once again before even a basic scenario like that if you were in windows
code would require you to drop down to media foundation but now.
Since I'm in...two-d I can use the draw text as part of the canvas drawing session
when two-d the overly some text so let's go ahead and run that.
Once again it's
going to take a bit to build because this is all compiling again with project and as we come up now I'm
going-to go ahead and overlay all the different configure this again with all the different overlays.
Our base one that's pretty cool.
...that overlay...the three kid ones.
I'm going to plea this you'll see we have tax drawn.
We have the one that we have all the videos
obvious is graphics accelerated it's all in csharp so you can see even though
...overlying text...overlying for videos on-base video there's no glitches
and performance...it all just runs perfectly smoothly.
Okay, now we're kind of stepping it up a
bits as ball would say network cooking with fire so that's actually move this along.
And, later we're actually going to see one of our partners what kind of cool stuff they've done with that custom composite are
So, let's talk about effects let's say I want to do it some type of image filter that
applying to the video before no,...went out to msdn I grabbed
are official sample and here's how to do a gray-scale effect in a windows store app about two
thousand lines of media foundation transform code all a lot of plumbing and everything like that
once again media foundation incredibly flexible incredibly powerful
kinda overkill for a lot of things using this new model we're talking about a
ninety lines of code which that boils down to basically five maybe six lines of
...decode so about a ninety six percent reduction in code to
do basic video...with this new model.
Now this new model there's kind of three key things that we talk about that
we like about this model first of all I imagine it's universal windows platform based
so you write your effect once it'll run on windows
they'll run on windows phone it'll run on xbox all that kind of stuff so once again allows you
to focus on the things that you care about and...going to be up...for your users.
One of the other thing is the course using existing libraries and code
since we interop everything as just a direct three-d surface and a direct three-d
device if you have the existing cheaters like direct actuators...ll
shoulders you can use direct three-d to actually apply your own custom shatters to these video
...if you want to use the
...imaging sdk we also have support for another construct called so
for software bitmap which is a common piece of technology that allows you to interop easily with
the...imaging sdk or other...out there that allow you to do cpu
based image processing and as well as we just saw one two-d and the other thing is it's cry
...usable across the entire media stack so while we're showing...show this in
the use of media composition this is stuff that you can easily apply the use of
...to media elements to media capture to media
trans coder any of those other media apis so once again you create
the effect once in a very powerful way
and you can use it anywhere you want across any device family across any media api.
So, let's actually show the implementation of an...
Rather than talking...you about what all this looks like let's actually just show it to-you...action.
So, one thing that I need to do on that basis video
let's add-in effect to it so adding in effect we have these
video affect definitions this is part of the api...shipped...windows phony point one.
So, I'm going to creates
...that I'm going to create a new video...definition and I'm going to
pass in this new saturation video effects that we're doing.
You might ask why this extra...role of a video fact definition I can I just
...instance of an effect well one of the major uses the media composition
is it's basically just a graph that represents operations you want to its in the typical
nonlinear editing it's not destructive so it's just defining the intention of the operations and
what you can do is you wire up the entire media composition and you can
actually purses that to a file and save it as a project and then load it late load
it later so this way we can low by having that acid or the runtime class name from
...rt we can actually load those only ads needed and it allows us to kind of
...we inflate the media composition graph?
let's implement the saturation video...once again you'll see it's just implementing
...interface I basic video...which is a new interface and windows ten
...a boils down to once again the setting coding properties that here we're creating a new wintry
...canvas device with a direct three-d device from the media pipeline and it's
basically process frame method if we look at the context you'll see there's
...input frame and output frame so we give you the input frame you give us the
result in the output frame and then we will use that in the rest of the pipeline.
So,...do this let's do the same thing where I'm going to
set up when two-d have a basic things of using the canvas drawing session
to render to the output bitmap and grabbing input bitmap.
Once again this is a...two-d saturation...formula
...zero...gray-scale you can see just a couple lines of code to do gray-scale
...as opposed to that two thousand lines of...code but I kinda want to make it a
little cooler so one of things I have is in the app
you might have seen a slide bar while the video is running I want
to actually control that sly bar in change the parameters to the effect
while the video is running so that a user can perhaps preview how they
want the effect to look and then snap-on that value so everything in the
property set configuration or in the configuration of the effect is based on
property sets I've created this property set that if we look here.
I'm passing in a saturation value based on that slider and all I need to do is when I
create the effect.
Of this effect I'm also going to give it that configuration and then in my
affects every time I process of frame.
I'm going to read from it me create this
parameter so in set.
Set properties...different method we give you the property sets that was
given by the initial when we configured the effects.
And, then instead of...
What's read that property so every frame I'm going to read that property.
We'll go ahead and build that and run this.
After build this allow us to press play on the video
...actually tweak the slider value while the videos running I'm going to have
all the videos to show you what we're talking about performance wise you can see already the preview.
The preview has already sat fully saturated communicate...overlays again.
And, hit...you can see we have the overlays going and defying
...slider while the videos playing.
Nci...full control over this no
...anything is still gpu accelerated doing everything I need to you.
Ok.
So, this
is a quick one what's actually before I bring my partner up on stage.
I want to show you some cool stuff that.
David and
...did the in the audience somewhere I'm pretty sure
...they are there in the front-row so there the creators of movie maker eight-point one
on windows phone one of the top paid apps in the store and we worked with them with this new api
say hey guys we want you to go create some cool stuff with this so I want to show off what they
actually did for us in a very short amount of time actually
to show you the our of this...keep fingers crossed that are reboot the machine...
Break this demo.
So, this is a preview specifically for
the build conference of movie maker ten that they worked on.
You can see I can play it and then I'm scrolling through and eigen
...clips and all that kind of stuff the cool thing I want to show you...transition support
so...overlays here's a simple fade you'll see you can fade to the next one.
Let's do a slide I'm actually going to do a different
using animation let's balance it out.
From the top and let's zoom on it when we're started.
Play that's.
You'll see boom group.
Let's get fun though I'm on a.
Is where we cross our fingers hope that this works?
Because I want to show you some of the cooler ones let's do something called slices.
Okay, that's pretty cool.
...alternate...
Number this is all csharp code I think davis
...about ten to eleven cot lines of csharp code okay that was cool.
This is the more cool button I like that all the way up to five hundred let's go up to
five hundred slices and see how this performs.
Let's look at that again now when I played again actually look at the right side of the video and you can
see the original video as we're doing the effect is still animated it's still playing
...processing the frame every time.
We are not once again csharp seven-eleven lines of code I think they said the build this entire app
to crm thirty hours something like that thirty hours to bake a lot of the time
with learning when two-d because it's a bit of a different kind of
...to get into if you've been using the libya imaging sdk or something like that.
...get moi.
Very cool stuff.
So, I'm going to pass...
Is going to come up here and talk
to-you about some of the next stuff that we're working on in the creative space?
All right let's see if you-can get this party rolling.
...started the party with video stuff let's talk about audio stuff.
Creative audio experiences has been a focus for us in windows
stand in general we wanted to make it easier than ever for you guys to write creative
interactive and music applications understand and what does this mean for you guys
what this means is that you guys can concentrate on writing code that makes your
app unique and your...special instead of having to spend time writing code that is
like the underlying pipeline...foundation park and the first part that we
did is invest in maybe some of you may remember that
last year and build jason introduced the preview version of...when
...media apis so why don't we invest in media in the first-place we
invested in mediad because as a lot of you guys who write music apps
...musicians themselves null mute...is the glue that holds...
music creation together is used to connect and control all kinds of devices...
choose to...computers controllers digital instrument synthesizers
women...also used to control some lighting equipment
it's a pretty fascinating protocol so we release this as a preview api
mostly in new get form for visual studio within list this to get feedback
from you guys for the kind of features capabilities that you want to see in the space
and some of the biggest feedback has been that you want to see this not as a new
get package for windows or visual studio...you want to see this big into the platform
...first step towards operating this feedback has been to actually go ahead and
...this into the platform...now available on all of windows ten?
Universal a platforms but what
...this really mean instead of talking apart editing it's more exciting to show you guys
are demo so let me go ahead and show you guys this demo of a little lap that
we have written let's see if demo...are with us.
Okay, how many of, you know, what the...
Okay,
a few of, you know, for those of you...don't know this is a innovation launch pad it's
a media controller it's got a bunch of buttons that you push the same media
compliance the device of the other end of this connection here I have a computer
it used to create all kinds of cool scenarios you they should just go online search for videos people
do some amazing stuff with this and today we're going to use this in somewhat
nontraditional sense we're not going to use this to send commands the computer we're
going to do the other way we're going to send commands to this device from
the pc and the combines that we're going to send is to turn on some...eds which are under
need these buttons we're going to make it look like a leader...so let's see if this works.
Okay, we have this here
so I hit connect to launch part and then I
...do cool stuff can...see this can you guys...what it says.
Okay, it says hello windows stent
...what it says this is all cool but what does this mean
for a universal windows platform api you can do this with any windows api right where it
is really cool is the our I have here a roxbury
pie running windows ten another motivation launch fired connected to the
raspy...I'm going to...deployed this exact same code to the raspy pi over
here without changing a single line of code and show you guys how that's going to work.
Ok.
So, this is actually running on the rest body pipe exact same
lab zero...changes all I did was change the target and
...it cyclic connector lunch parrot.
Do cool stuff same thing over again?
How cools that exact same code running on a pc
...but if I can sorry...to
...guys imagine...it's such a little tiny device so this gives us the this shows
the our of what the universal windows of platform can really do?
So, let's go back over here but that's not all sure we put
...bigoted into the platform and we made part of the universal windows
But, we've done more than that you guys give us a lot of good feedback and
...this feedback and reprint inc the first one is
...device access this means that more than one app can actually communicate
two-way connected media device simultaneously what this means for...is that you can now
write your apps without having to worry about what other app is accessing this media device
you can concentrate on your creative scenarios instead of having to worry about devices
...piece of feedback we received was that you wanted to use the in build sent
...platform as a media output device so we made this accessible
...through the media apis the inbox microsoft
...table g ascent is now listed does just another media output device it
will be enumerated in the media apis you guys can usage you can play
sounds we ate all of that good stuff the only thing to note is that the sounds are pretty large
in sayce especially when it comes to things like roxbury pie
...so we've made this available as a framework package from the
windows store so you need to declares as a dependency in your...makes manifest in your visual
studio project and it will be pulled from the store dynamically upon app launch.
The other part that we also did for the synthesizer is technique
increase the performance and the latency characteristics of the synthesizer and that's not our
...continuing to improve the performance of the synthesizer in future releases and
the other aspect that we improved for many is device naming.
The traditionally windows has had some we've gotten feedback
the names that the media api show or not intuitive so right
now what we do is we try to query the firmware of the...media device to see if
there is a logical name that exists over there and be...doctoral so
when you're creating the devices to your api you find names that you would
identify it for the devices as well as the ports.
So, all of this is great board what else did we do in the field
of interactive audio what we have done is we've gotten some feedback
...it we have a bunch of audio apis but they're not always the
easiest to use because some audio apis a very-high-level submodular apis
a video specialized and let's walk through that with the
simple scenario how many of you here have done karaoke at some point.
Yeah, I'm all right.
For those of you would never done it today might be
your lucky day we'll see if we can get you on stage singing karaoke with me at the end of the session.
...so let's draw the block diagram of what we need for
...walked away before we actually going to discussion of these apis.
For those of you...don't have done...okay, you know,
the scenario...simple you have a microphone you have a speaker you have a connection right
what's important also here is that you need
to connection that is low latency it is important to have low latency because nobody wants to hear an echo of
themselves when they're singing into the microphone and what you also need to have is a backing
crack...to have something like...that
you play in the background when you're singing on top of it that...to...your...
We're going to make this scenario slightly more interesting with the potential for blackmail
by a recording this to a file so whoever singing we're
going to record this to a file and this is pretty simple right but these lines you see
or getting messy so let's clean that up but keep the scenario simple let's add a sub
makes a or a mixing let's mix these two signals
...still simple the mixer has to inputs
...output pretty straightforward right I want to make the scenario you
even more interesting I want to apply some kind of an effect on my
mixing mixed signal let's say in this case I want to apply
...river signal I want to make myself sound like I'm singing
in a cave or maybe singing in a studio
and auditorium or something like that and
...singer I will admit that but I don't want to sound terrible especially when the file
is being recorded so maybe I want to have some kind...auto tune or something like this for
see the microphone that makes me sound not so terrible and to make
this scenario even more
interesting let's add a visual aspect to with the takes a
...this data...and maybe does some spectrum analysis and
...waveform things like that and let's now tabulated all of the
things that we need in order to accomplish the...the bottom over there particular
right I mean there's nothing there that we can talk about and we all want things to be easy to code.
So, let's discuss this in terms of what we have today how would you do
So, let me paint a picture the
appear landscape today is that you have some high-level choices you have say the media
element which can do some of these things not a whole lot but it is high-level
...easy-to-use right...it's...api is available all of the
...projected languages csharp javascript etc and then you
have media capture which again cannot do other things but
...still easy-to-use and the problem is there's no easy way to string these
two aps together in order to accomplish the scenario so what are...choices to be help.
Juicing...to falling off the complexity cliff.
That's what you have to do in order to use cplus-plus api they're hard to use nobody wants to go to cplus-plus unless you
have...should gives you a lot of our but with that our also comes a lot of
complexity you have x audio you have was happy which are the apis and cplus-plus
...native staff but the problem with that is even things
like playing back a simple mpthree file is not easy why
because x...and what have we don't understand the concept of mpthree which means to
write a simple karaoke hap you have to know rule your own mpthree parser
item sign up for dot I don't want to write my own mpthree parser just because they want
...simple karaoke app same thing with saving to a file if I want to write the to like recording
...and pthree or something I don't want to have to
write my own will mpthree parser in order to figure out where to put what
...in order to solve this the introduced a
...api in windows stand called audio...
Liked name suggests audio graph is a graph base dpi what is a graph
adp I mean it means you have the concept of
nodes the nodes accomplish different things you can make them do different things and you
just random along and you realize whatever scenario you want.
And, lets it as you can see it suffice it fulfills all
of...and this is an api that has been designed with interactive audio in
mind you don't have to twist other apis that were not designed for interactive audio to relays
your scenario plus you get to work in the high-level language like csharp even all
if your coding over there and the best part it's a universal windows platform api so
trans everywhere including...to.
What does this mean...audio graph so let's translate?
The objects that we saw the
...into audio...objects.
The audio crafts uses...very similar concept like
...calls these objects nodes that it strings them along together and the
nor names are pretty self-explanatory you have your device input node which
is what mike you have your diverse output node which is what is speaker file input file
output similar for you have your submits node and like jason mentioned he introduced
the I basing video affect similarly you have the I basic argue effect that can be
used altered the universal windows platform apis that you can
use to process data you can write-in csharp...without having to worry
about writing heavy-duty cplus-plus score just to have a simple effect
in this case we were he was doing gray-scale in our case we're doing a is
...analysis.
So, let's.
Move to visual studio where we're going to try and create
this api or create this karaoke up with the stuff that we've shown.
Okay, so, what do you guys think?
That the...different components that need to be there we looked at a diagram
let's build each of those diagrams or each of those nodes that we
sign the previous diagram encode the first we need to create...audio
...instance in order to bind all of this together before we create a audio
...instance what...need to do
...normally contributed with something in this case you can't...out what is called
a settings object so you first create the sightings object and then you pasta
...the settings object into the creation of audio
graph so this creating...with the setting for
simply sake in our current demo we're just going to.
The only settings we're going to specify is the audio
...category and david who is
goo speaking in the coming days is going to delve deep into what these audio categories
mean but for now we're playing a media related stuff so we're going to pick media this is the
only non optional part of the settings object we're going to clean the settings object and we have
an asynchronous method...create the asic
...business audio graph it returns the result object the result
object has success or failure what kind of failure and
...succeeded it has a pointer to the
...object that you then safe.
These enough rightly lines of code...the to create audio
...and now we need to do what stringing together for
...sound from the speakers.
That's a two lines of code is all you need to be able to make a connection to the speaker
you have a line that says create device output node similarly returns
...just like you saw previously boom that's
...the next part is going to be creating a
device input node for the microphone.
That's it you need to provide a media capture category over here.
Please ignore the...printed...running preview bits of windows and as you can...
You create a media of the device input
...asynchronous methods and all of these calls are unlocking new return the
result object in which you have a device input and that's a pretty simple right.
And, then what else do we need to we need to player device a you need
to file input node to play a recording dot mpthree?
In this case we're going to make...funky and...twinkle,
twinkle little star who here knows to sound twinkle, twinkle little star.
Seriously noone okay we're going to make...
We're going to see if we can get somebody that knows
the song so the real audio
...part is the last two lines the first two lines you open the storage find their standard aps that you guys
...before standard csharp apis you open
a storage file in this case I have a twinkle, twinkle little star dot mpthree
inside my project eye-opening and I need to save my
file into...like we talked about so we're going to...file output node.
That's it the first-line creates the storage file and then the second part
and the third part actually is the audio graphical pretty simple
right is anybody everybody with me so far anybody did I lose.
...is enough so you'll notice here ...created recording
that wave but that's not what we talk about we talked about creating recording and
mpthree the default option for audio graft saves to recording at wave so we're going
to mpthree over here by changing the filename isn't enough?
So, we're going to create.
...going to do this.
These are.
For aps already exists.
That's it that's all you need to create an mpthree file you wanted to create a...or you wanted to create a
wm a file but if you want to change the encoding properties you just
...and customize the your profile that's all you need to do.
And, then we're mostly done right what else is left the
submits node so we need to create the submits node which is literally one-line.
That's it creates a mix not boom but then this doesn't create
...input...incoming and outgoing connection so we're going to just create
and input outgoing connections we're going to wire them up.
So, you have for...it has to inputs...
outputs the numbers that you see over there is the gain.
So, in this case the microphone I want to push up again so I can actually hear my own
weiss above the backing track which is why the phili input has
...suppress the gain of...zero-point-five whereas the mike of...high and...five-point-zero.
And, then I'm going to create a custom effect
that jason talked about using a basic audio
...that in this case I'm not going to do a full spectrum analyzer
instead all I'm doing is looking at the volume of the signal and returning the decibel
value that represent visual we're...going to the implementation of the
code over here but we will discuss that in the st samples.
And, let's see if this compiles.
And,...compiling do I have a volunteer for somebody to come and
seeing this with me anyone all right, come on, up.
...everybody...
All right.
So, we're going to use this microphone...intuit.
So, let's wait and to compiles, compiles, compiles.
All right.
All right moi.
World so.
Okay, everybody given behind the mouth.
...I told
you were going to have a party over here so let's see where it actually recorded
it recorded in the music folder you have your recording dot mpthree
overhear.
...double-click this and make sure that...actually place.
You guys see...
...was fun wasn't.
It's all this is all great.
So, let's.
What we haven't covered is we're doing a kind?
We're running a little shards so we're going to skip the custom effects that we're going to have the
...the audio
...provides let me just run you guys to a quick simple echo effect let me show you the code.
So, all they do is create and
...definition and I have parameters and I just added to my
...node a by default its enabler and I don't want
to enable unless I click on a button to actually say enable this effect so I go
ahead and disabled...I have...you why...click...to...and.
This is...great so let's move to this.
the karaoke...fun but there is one part that we
...talked about...say latency was important for a karaoke upward really
haven't discussed how or why we address latency first
let me go a little bit deeper into the topic of latency because this requires some level of
detail and I want to make sure that you guys realize all of the work when the
microsoft has done in this area four-wheel for latency?
First we heard a lot of feedback...latency is very important for interactive
audio scenarios and just any kind of audio scenario in general for the pro audio
creative professionals...lot-of feedback we've taken this seriously and we have done a lot of
work in windows tend to reduce latency typical numbers,
for example, like device like the surface pro tree in windows eight-point one used to
...milliseconds round-trip we'll talk a little bit in a couple of minutes about
what...fifteen milliseconds means and when you upgraded
to windows can you will get a round-trip millie a latency of about ten
milliseconds this is a you should get similar numbers on your hp specter
that-you received today as well this will obviously depend on the device and the diverse
will get into a little bit of details in a couple of minutes what why?
So, let's bring them time talking about what the fifty milliseconds
is first there are two large
sector categories of latency that most people talk about the first one is touch to sound
...sound is the time you hear the argue from the moment
to touch your touch-screen.
The second part is a round-trip latency round-trip latency is when you
have a microphone you sing...the audio flows through the capture
stack into the audio engine and then...flows back through the
...part of the speakers and it's the time you...into
the microphone to the time you hear yourself and this is the part that we're going to be concentrating on
this session because that's more related audio we're not going to...stack.
So, since I talk about the audio stuff let me paint you picture of what the
audio subsystem looks like this is how audio looks like
on windows where you have the application on top you have the hardware and the bottom you have the audio engine that
...in between and...doctor each other with buffers the buffers are standard
is our ten millisecond buffered that you used to communicate between each other the majority of the work that we've
done in windows terror a huge amount of work that we put into the argue engine has been to
re architect and redesign the audio engine that on the exact same hardware you will get a minimum
of fifteen milliseconds the savings in the round-trip
scenario but what we have also done is enabled support for smaller
buffers smaller buffers means that each layer has to wait less for the other
layer-two handed data and this obviously requires hardware support and therefore device
driver support so we've enabled new methods for the device to
announce these capabilities to the audio engine and then application can then query
these capability aim to be audio engine to figure out what kind-of for
support happens on that particular device all of this is great.
But, we still haven't talked about hoping use latency in audio
graph...all of this is...it takes like a million lines of code to use low latency
autograph right so let me just jump back to visual studio for
a quick second to show you exactly how many lines of code it is.
To use low latency audio graph.
You remember those settings object be created to create the audio graph.
All we need to do here is say's settings dot.
Quantum size selection mode and we have to say quantum say
selection more dot...latency that's a...
line of code that is all it takes to go into the lowest latency more than that particular
hardware device so if I now recompile this hardware this karaoke app that
...have on this particular hardware you will hear an even lower latency
although that's mostly more obvious for the person singing...because for the person hearing you don't really know
when them all the words...smart sowe're going to skip the
...particular demo of...and...move back into our point.
...so, that's all of the work that we did inwindows
ten for audio and.
If nothing else we want you to remember these top points when you guys
need to them because we covered a...the first we want you do
remember reducing talked about for media composition...was introduced in windows
for a pipeline we bring this into the universal windows platform we
increased performance as well as we have additional...capabilities like
...and overlays and the other stuff we talk about today is
maybe?
We looked at a very core demo of how many runs in the universal windows platform using raspy
...as an example and we also introduced a
brand-new api for interactive audio applications called audio...
And, we introduced low latency argue...the work that we did in there I want to say that low
latency is a complicated topic and it's a very deep topic so we didn't really do justice
overhear to cover all of the details we will be...a white paper with a
lot of details on all the work that we did in low latency and what how you can use it in audio...and
...copy and all of the different goodness is how you can
query the driver to figure out of the stuff that it better
...that's not all there's more to come the
...you will see that
the creative media experiences angle is receiving a lot of coverage there's
...news to come in the keynote...which I think you guys would really like?
And, I want to stress
this is only the first step of many were continuing to make improvements to make windows
...robust platform for creative media experiences were doing a lot of work
...the latency don't even further so we're listening to feedback and we're also going to be
there at a three-year and summer nam later this year talking about all of the work that we
did an audio so if any of you guys are going to be their
please locus up we're going to have sessions their to dive deep into this as well so call-to-action
what do we want you guys to do first we want you to go to the dead-center we want you
to guys to download the latest windows ten the preview release and then we
want you guys to download the st samples virtual far more examples
...samples and what we talked about in the session today because we only have so much time?
And, then we also want to download the visual studio and go party on these...go play with
it figure out what works what doesn't work...all of that and jason here
I want to give a plug...to his get a project where we're going to be posting of the
demo code that we short today for you guys to play
...will be a couple of ...time before we actually post
the get around to posting the code samples and get hub...jason has a
old examples from last year's...either choose you the our and the subsystem the
audio subsume what it can do and he also has a blog that will talk
about our investments in the creative media experience space that I highly recommend you guys
...is going to be...coverage...audio and video topics over there.
So, that...project right now is just a placeholder so we expect to get stuff up there
starting rolling in the next couple of days as the public bits become available as the public when
two-d bits become available all I can stop then we'll start really publishing that media
...how to repository yes I want to stress that all of this
as possible because you give us feedback you told us what you value you told us what you want to seeing a
platform so please keep that feedback coming if something doesn't particularly suit your use
case...scenario tell us because we want to know we want to build a platforms the
dreamy work for you guys and aps at work for you guys so keep us posted tell us what works
tell us what doesn't work how we can improve what you would like to see all of that.
Gratin thanks everybody'd...we have or.
So, for questions we're running
...time you come up in...us here we're also going to be in the windows insider lounge for the next
...you have for the next hour and a half to do you tweet like do you have a
twitter account online ok so you can also feel free to contact me on twitter it's
...apps j...eighty-eight same as my get name and all that kind of
stuff we would love to hear from you guys so absolutely contact with
...thanks everybody thank you?